#### Contact

susan.white1010@comcast.net

www.linkedin.com/in/susan-white-rn-bsn-mba-81334014 (LinkedIn)

#### Top Skills

Organizational Leadership
Team Building
Mentoring

Certifications NE-BC

**CNOR** 

# Susan White, RN, BSN, MBA

Interim/Transitional Leader - CNO and Perioperative Services Sugar Land, Texas

### Summary

Nurse executive and leader within large, academic teaching facilities and small, community hospitals with experience in hospital construction, turnaround situations, mentoring and coaching staff. Interested in patient safety, quality of care and best practices to positively impact patient care.

Specialties: Perioperative management, work place environment, quality initiatives, patient safety, LOS initiatives, finance & comanagement model start up.

## Experience

Western Connecticut Health Network (WCHN)
Interim OR Manager Danbury Hospital/ RSC
November 2017 - October 2018 (1 year)
Danbury, CT

Managed all aspects of OR operations @ Danbury OR until Aug. 2018 and RSC from Sept. 3rd-Oct. 3rd 2018.

SIH - Memorial Hospital Carbondale Interim OR Manager January 2017 - June 2017 (6 months) Carbondale, Illinois

Bay Area Regional Medical Center Chief Nursing Officer January 2014 - August 2016 (2 years 8 months) Webster, Texas

Leading the hospital's clinical team to a successful opening of what will be the best hospital in the Bay Area for patients, physicians and staff. A state-of-the-art 104 bed acute care hospital where medicine meets technology. Responsible for Med/Surg, ICU, IMU, Telemetry, ED, Perioperative Services, Endoscopy, Invasive & Non-Invasive, Laboratory Services, Respiratory Therapy, Imaging and Pharmacy.

Houston Physicians' Hospital Chief Nursing Officer March 2012 - December 2013 (1 year 10 months) Webster, TX

CNO for 21 bed surgical hospital responsible for Nursing, UR/Case Management, Pharmacy and Dietary Services.

Houston Physicians' Hospital of Texas Interim CNO December 2011 - March 2012 (4 months)

St. Luke's Patients Medical Center Chief Nursing Officer January 2011 - September 2011 (9 months)

Responsibilities included ED, Med/Surg, Cath Lab, Pharmacy, Quality, Risk Management, Education, Infection Control, Food and Nutrition Services and Wound Care. During my short tenure I worked with nursing leadership, staff and IT to implement the Meditech electronic medication administration record, and participated in the Meditech upgrade. Initiated weekly executive meetings, Nurse Council meetings, town hall meetings and monthly department director meetings. I held nursing focus groups and nursing forums. Implemented a SWAT nurse to assist nursing departments during peak census times. Implemented daily productivity tool to manage nursing FTEs. Implemented numerous Core Measure initiatives such as standard order sets, progress notes, forms revisions, concurrent chart reviews, to improve outcomes.

Huntsville Memorial Hospital - affiliate of Memorial Hermann Healthcare System Chief Nursing Officer November 2007 - November 2010 (3 years 1 month)

Huntsville Memorial Hospital is an affiliate of the Memorial Hermann Healthcare System with an executive team from MHHS providing the leadership to the hospital. HMH is a 123 bed, not-for-profit, rural hospital owned by the Walker County Hospital Corporation, leased from WCHD with net revenue of 71 million, employing approximately 600, 480 FTEs.

Responsibilities include administrative oversight for nursing services, inclusive of Home Health, ICU, ED, Med/Surg, Surgery, Perioperative Services, ASC, Joe G. Davis LVN School, IP Rehab, Customer Relations, Observation Unit, OB, Education, Infection Control, Quality/Risk, Outpatient Rehab,

Cardiopulmonary. Responsibilities have included Pharmacy, Wound Care Center and Case Management/Social Services. Manage 14 direct reports, approximately 190 FTEs and function with the other Executives as the acting CEO in the absence of the CEO. Combined expense budgets total approximately 16.6 million and gross patient revenues of 70 million.

Accomplishments include:

Executive sponsor for electronic clinical documentation, API ActiveStaffer (implemented) & Acutality (in progress)

Strategic planning for 10 bed observation unit- opened in 3 mos.

Opened Forensic Unit in 6 weeks

Implemented a customer service excellence program

Patient satisfaction percentile improvement FY09 - 25th percentile, FY10 YTD - 53rd percentile

Developed and implemented a Recruitment & Retention strategy for nursing services - retention rate 97% FY 10 YTD

Developed and implemented a case management strategy for the hospital Contracted pharmacy services to meet regulatory requirements

Replaced ED physician group 2008

Replaced Anesthesia group 2010

# Memorial Hermann Healthcare System CNO

December 1994 - November 2010 (16 years)

Director Perioperative Services for 7 years and CNO for 9 years.

As CNO had responsibility at some point in the 9 years for all depts. except business office/finance related depts. For example all nursing depts., food & nutritions, EVS, Medical Staff Office, Therapy Depts.

### Memorial Hermann Sugar Land Hospital Chief Patient Care Officer February 2001 - July 2007 (6 years 6 months)

Memorial Hermann Sugar Land Hospital is a 77 bed, acute care, community hospital with net revenue of \$59 million, opening as a replacement hospital in December 2006, employing 450. It is one of 11 hospitals in the Memorial Hermann Healthcare System, the largest not-for-profit healthcare system in Texas with annual net revenues of \$2.5 billion. MHHS is the third largest private employer in Houston.

Responsibilities included administrative oversight for nursing services inclusive of ICU, Med/Surg, OR, PACU, Endoscopy, Day Surgery, Perinatal, Anesthesia, Education, Volunteer Services, Customer Relationship Management, Information Systems, Quality and Risk Management, Infection Control, Respiratory and Cardiopulmonary. Have had administrative oversight for Imaging, Chaplaincy, Case Management, Food and Nutrition, Medical Staff Services, Environmental Services, and Inpatient Rehabilitation. Managed 9 direct reports and approximately 175 FTEs. Combined expense budgets totaled approximately \$14 million and gross patient revenues of \$53 million.

#### Accomplishments include:

Design and construction for replacement hospital - on time, on budget
Successful move of patients from closing hospital to new hospital
Design and successful implementation of patient/family centered model of care
Implementation of EMAR, clinical documentation, CPOE, Perioperative
documentation and Case Tracking - on time, on budget
Design and successful implementation of shared governance model
Administrative oversight for implementation of Preferred Physician Referral
Center

Administrative sponsor for implementation of Admission Center - opened successfully in six weeks

Cath Lab - Memorial Hermann Southeast Hospital Director Perioperative Services
December 1994 - January 2001 (6 years 2 months)

Memorial Hermann Southeast Hospital is a 225 bed community hospital and one of 11 hospitals in the MHHS located in Southeast Houston.

Responsibilities included operational oversight for OR, PACU, Anesthesia, Cath Lab and Endoscopy, interim Director of Day Surgery. Responsible for a \$4 million operating budget, 65 FTEs.

Accomplishments included:

Managed a \$2 million cath lab renovation project
Agency reduction
Implemented perioperative internship for new recruits
Chair of system perioperative council
Neurosurgery program development
28% increase in surgical volume
Successful JCAHO surveys

#### Policy and procedure development

The Methodist Hospital
Head Nurse/Educator/Staff Nurse Operating Rooms
January 1985 - December 1994 (10 years)

The Methodist Hospital System
Head Nurse Perioperative Services
1985 - December 1994 (9 years)
Houston, TX

Perioperative staff nurse, clinical coordinator, educator and head nurse in all specialties except ENT and Ophthamology.

# Houston Community College Faculty

January 1987 - January 1988 (1 year 1 month)

Faculty for the Surgical Technologist Program.

### Hospital Nursing Service

Staff Nurse

October 1984 - December 1984 (3 months)

Interim perioperative assignments

#### Orthopaedic & Arthritic Hospital

Staff Nurse

January 1984 - June 1984 (6 months)

Circulated and scrubbed for Orthopaedic procedures and worked as a staff nurse for pre and post op orthopaedics.

The Methodist Hospital
Clinical Coordinator/Staff Nurse
July 1980 - November 1983 (3 years 5 months)

Orthopaedic & Arthritic Hospital Staff Nurse July 1979 - June 1980 (1 year)

The Methodist Hospital Staff Nurse January 1978 - March 1979 (1 year 3 months)

## Education

2006 graduate of J&J Wharton Business School Nurse Executive MBA  $\cdot$  (2006 - 2006)

OLLU

MBA, Business · (1995 - 1997)

**UTHSC Houston** 

Bachelor of Science, Nursing · (1991 - 1993)

George Brown College

Diploma, Nursing · (1975 - 1977)